Before we can begin analyzing data or using it to train our learning algorithms,
在开始分析数据或用数据训练学习算法之前
we need to clean it.
我们需要清理数据
This means we need a way to detect and correct errors in our data.
也就是说我们要想办法检测并修正数据里的错误
While any given dataset can have many types of
数据集的劣质数据有很多种
bad data such as outliers or incorrect values,
比如异常值或错误值
the type of bad data we encounter almost always is missing values.
但最常见的是缺失值
As we saw earlier,
我们之间就说过
Pandas assigns the value NaN,
Pandas 会将 NaN
or not a number to missing data.
赋给缺失数据 表示此处非数字
In this section, we will learn how to detect and deal with these NaN values.
本节将讲解检测并处理这些 NaN 值的方法
In this DataFrame, we have three NaN values.
在这个 DataFrame 中 我们有三个 NaN 值
One in store one,
一个在 store 1
and two in store three.
两个在 store 3
However, in cases where we load
但如果我们往 DataFrame 加载的数据集太庞大
very large datasets into a DataFrame possibly with millions of items,
比如加载了数百万个项
the number of NaN values isn't easily visualized like this.
那 NaN 值的数目就没这么一目了然了
For these cases, we can use a combination of
这种时候 我们可以结合多个方法
methods to count the number of NaN values in our data.
对数据里的 NaN 值数量进行统计
This combines to is null and sum methods to count
要用到的方法有 isnull 和 sum
the number of NaN values in our DataFrame. Let's break this down.
结合使用这两个方法 就能统计 DataFrame 里 NaN 值的数目了 我们一步一步来
The is null method returns a DataFrame with
方法 isnull 会返回一个 DataFrame
a Boolean for each value in the store items DataFrame.
将 DataFrame store_items 的每个值替换成布尔值
True, when the value is NaN.
如果值为 NaN 布尔值就为真
In Pandas, logical true values have the numerical value
在 Pandas 中 数字 1 表示逻辑真值
one and logical false values have the numerical value zero.
数字 0 表示逻辑假值
Therefore, we can count the number of NaN values by
因此 要知道 NaN 值的数量
counting the number of logical true values from this DataFrame.
只需统计 DataFrame 里逻辑真值的数量即可
Using sum ones gives us a number of NaNs in each column.
用方法 sum 来统计 1 的数量 就可以知道每一列有多少个 NaN 值了
We use sum again to get the total number of NaNs for the entire DataFrame.
再调用一次方法 sum 统计整个 DataFrame NaN 值的数量
Instead of counting the number of NaN values,
我们也可以不统计 NaN 值的数量
we can also do the opposite and count the number of non-NaN values with the count method.
反其道而行 用方法 count 来统计非 NaN 值的数量
Now that we know how to find out if our dataset has any NaN values,
知道了怎么找出数据集里的 NaN 值
the next step is to decide what to do with them.
下一步就是决定怎么处理这些值了
In general, we have two options.
总地来说 我们有两个选择
We can either remove or replace missing values.
删除或替换
To remove them, we can use the drop na method.
要删除缺失值 可以用方法 dropna
We can set the axis parameter to zero to eliminate any rows with NaN values.
我们可以设参数 axis 为 0 删除任何有 NaN 值的行
We can also set axis to one to eliminate any columns with NaN values.
也可以设 axis 为 1 删除任何有 NaN 值的列
The dropna method drops these rows or columns out of place.
方法 dropna 是在其它地方删除行和列的
Meaning, the original DataFrame is not modified.
也就是说 原 DataFrame 不会出现改动
You can remove them in-place by setting the keyword in-place to true like this.
像这样把关键字 inplace 设为 True 你就可以在原 DataFrame 上删除行和列了
Now, instead of eliminating NaN values,
现在我们不删除 NaN 值了
let's replace them with actual values.
而是用具体数值来替换这些值
As an example, we could choose to replace all NaNs with the value zero.
我们可以把所有 NaN 值替换成 0
The fillna method can be used for this.
为此 我们可以用方法 fillna
We can also replace NaNs with values from
我们也可以用前向填充 ffill
the previous row or column with something called forward filling.
以上一行或列的值来替换 NaN 值
This replaces each NaN with the value from the previous value along the given axis.
该方法会用给定轴上的前一个值来填充相应的 NaN 值
Here's the original DataFrame again.
这是原始 DataFrame
Notice that the two NaN values in store three
注意 store 3 的两个 NaN 值
have been replaced with the previous values in their column.
已经被同一列的前值替换掉了
However, notice that the NaN value in store one did not get replaced.
但 store 1 里的 NaN 值并没有得到替换
That's because there were no previous values in
因为这一列没有前值
this column since NaN is the first value in this column.
NaN 是这一列的第一个值
However, if we do forward fill using the previous row values this won't happen.
如果我们用前一行的值来进行前向填充 这种事就不会发生
We see that in this case,
我们可以看到
all the NaN values have been replaced with the previous value in that row.
此时所有 NaN 值都替换成了同一行的前一个值
Similarly, you can choose to replace
同理 你也可以
the NaNs with the values that go after them in the DataFrame.
用 DataFrame 里的后一个值来填充相应的 NaN 值
This is known as backward filling.
这个过程叫做后向填充
This replaces each NaN with the next value in that column.
可以把 NaN 值替换成与其同列的后一个值
The NaN value in store one has been replaced by the next value in it's column.
store 1 里的 NaN 值已经替换成同列的后一个值了
But the two NaN values in store three did
但是 store 3 里的两个 NaN 值得不到替换
not since they are the last values in their columns.
因为它们是列里的最后一个值
The fillna method fills the NaN values out of place.
方法 fillna 不会在原 DataFrame 里填充 NaN 值
So, set the parameter in place to true if you want to modify the original DataFrame.
所以如果想修改原 DataFrame 请把参数 inplace 设为 True
We can also choose to replace NaNs by using different interpolation methods.
我们还可以用多种插值方法来替换 NaN 值
For example, this uses linear interpolation to
比如 这里用了线性插值
replace NaN values using the values along the column axis.
借助同轴 (列) 的值来替换 NaN 值
The two NaN values in store three have been replaced with linear interpolated values.
store 3 里的两个 NaN 值因而替换成了相应的线性插值
However, NaN value in store one did not get replaced since
但 store 1 的 NaN 值得不到替换
there is no data before it to allow the interpolation function to calculate a value.
因为前面没有数据 插值函数无法算出替换值
We can replace NaN values with linear interpolation using row values like this.
线性插值时 我们也可以像这样用同行的值来替换 NaN 值
Like the other methods we saw,
就像其它方法一样
the interpolate method replaces NaN values out of place.
插值方法不会在原 DataFrame 上替换 NaN 值